<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CLI Utils on Infinity Architect</title><link>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/</link><description>Recent content in CLI Utils on Infinity Architect</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cesun.info/linux/utils/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>GNU sed stream editor</title><link>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/sed/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/sed/</guid><description>The sed program is a line-based stream editor. In the big picture, it reads a line from input, applies modification if requested by script, and print the modified line to the output, and repeats until the whole input stream is consumed.
What sed Cannot sed doesn&amp;rsquo;t support Perl regex. Only POSIX BRE and ERE are available when a pattern needs to be specified; Among others, this means non-greedy matching is not possible with sed.</description></item><item><title>Userspace Printer Control</title><link>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/printer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/printer/</guid><description>lpr (line printer) - 打印 lpr FILE	打印FILE。将使用默认打印机。 lpr -P NAME	指定打印机名。注意-P不带NAME参数单独使用时有别的含义。
lpstat cups (not a executable? man 1 cups) lpq - 显示打印队列状态 lprm - 取消打印任务 cancel - 取消打印任务</description></item><item><title>Process Management CLI Utils</title><link>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/process/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/process/</guid><description>pgrep/ pwait / pkill from procps-ng These 3 tools support rich condition search on processes.
pwait/pkill by pid is not supported.
pgrep pgrep always prints a delimiter-separated (configurable by -d) list of pid.
Selectors are always logically intersected, i.e. all must match. List supplied to a single selector are always unioned. Use -v to negate the whole selector combination. 1# select processes whose EUID=1000, AND processes whose cmd name is exactly &amp;#39;code&amp;#39; 2pgrep -u 1000 -x code copy ps from procps-ng ps suffers from the curse of compatibility for multiple historical implementations.</description></item><item><title>GNU awk record TODO</title><link>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/awk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/linux/utils/awk/</guid><description>awk is a record-based CLI text editor. It first splits a text file into delimiter-separated segments known as records, then performs an action if a record matches a given pattern. It is generally considered a superior replacement for sed, but with its own extra complexity. gawk is GNU&amp;rsquo;s implementation of awk. On most Linux distros is a symlink to gawk:
# $ ls -hl `which awk` lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 4 Nov 4 2023 /usr/bin/awk -&amp;gt; gawk copy CLI invocation TODO</description></item></channel></rss>