<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DNS on Infinity Architect</title><link>https://cesun.info/net/dns/</link><description>Recent content in DNS on Infinity Architect</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cesun.info/net/dns/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BIND9 (Berkeley Internet Name Domain Server) Configs</title><link>https://cesun.info/net/dns/bind/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/net/dns/bind/</guid><description>Install the package from https://www.isc.org/software/bind/ or check the package manager of your Linux distro.
run the name server Run the named executable to start the name server.
For a test / debug launch, use -g flags
named by default turn itself into a background daemon; Use -f to prevent its disattachment and receive signals.
configs named upon its start up reads /etc/named.conf as the main config file.
options { directory &amp;#34;/var/named&amp;#34;; // the working directory contains zone files etc.</description></item><item><title>DNS as a general-purpose KV store: Model and Design</title><link>https://cesun.info/net/dns/model/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/net/dns/model/</guid><description>This article gives an overview of the design of the Domain Name System.
The Hierarchical Name Space &amp;amp; Domains In the center of the Domain Name System is the idea of a tree of names, known as the hierarchical namespace.
B U R C L I N L M O C X I S S X L C M I A D T C A H R I P L A L E S A ( e C m p t y V E I A s D S X t U I A r i I n N V g - E ) A N D E D R R A M S o R c I k - U a N D p I E e A C L t R r P i A s A Y C A C L E Each node on the tree is assigned a label, e.</description></item><item><title>DNS Message &amp; Resource Record Format</title><link>https://cesun.info/net/dns/format/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/net/dns/format/</guid><description>convention and glossaries 0 indicates the most significant bit. RR stands for Resource Record, see below. Message Format DNS is a request-response protocol. The query and the response share the same format which always starts with a header:
Q 0 R 1 O 2 p c o 3 d e 4 A 5 A T 6 C Q A N A R D N S R 7 I D C C C C D O O O O R U U U U 8 A N N N N T T T T 9 Z 1 0 1 1 1 2 R 1 3 C O D 1 4 E 1 5 a f c c c c l o o o o r a u u u u e g n n n n s s t t t t p o - o o o o n f f f f s s e e e R R R e n R R R m t s s s u b r s e i i i i t l e n n n o s e w t t t c i h h h h n e e e o q A A A t u n u d h e s t d e s w h i t e o t s i r r i a o i o m n s t n e e y a s c l I e t s D c i e s t o c e o i n t c f o i t n o i i ; n o t n s i .</description></item></channel></rss>