<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Computer Memory on Infinity Architect</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/</link><description>Recent content in Computer Memory on Infinity Architect</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cesun.info/ee/mem/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Memo: What Every Programmer Should Know About Memory</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/cpumemory/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/cpumemory/</guid><description>This is a memo for Ulrich Drepper&amp;rsquo;s What Every Programmer Should Know About Memory
https://people.freebsd.org/~lstewart/articles/cpumemory.pdf
Naming Unit:
GT/s: gigatransfer per seconds, i.e. billion or 10^9 MT/s: megatransfer per seconds, i.e. million or 10^6 DDR4-2666 means a DDR4 SDRAM chip is around 2666.67 MT/s.
Most commercial MM mounts 8 x8 chips per rank in order to provide a 64 bit global data bus. If the chip mounted is DDR4-2666, the whole module is named PC4-21300, because each transfer is 64 bits = 8 bytes, and 2666.</description></item><item><title>SDRAM Memory Modules</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/sdram-mm/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/sdram-mm/</guid><description>Memory module The name of a MM spec is usually like DDR4 (SDRAM) DIMM with PC4-12800 or PC4-2133.
DDR (Double Data Rate) means that the DQ lines of each chip are double pumped; 4th generation of this technology. SDRAM means synchronous dynamic RAM, and is usually omitted since it&amp;rsquo;s the default since 1990. DIMM (Dual In-line Memory Module) refers to the fact that the PCB has 2 rows of distinct pins on both side of the PCB.</description></item><item><title>SDRAM Chip Command &amp; Encoding</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/sdram-cmd/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/sdram-cmd/</guid><description>NOP: no op REF: REFRESH DES: deselect ACTIVATE(BG, BA, A[17:0]): open a row in a bank encoding:
The ACTIVATE command is used to open (activate) a row in a particular bank for subsequent access. One bank can only have 1 opened row at the same time.
timing restriction:
t_RRD_S (s for short): minimal interval user must wait btwn 2 ACTIVATEs in different bank group. t_RRD_L (l for long): minimal interval user must wait btwn 2 ACTIVATEs in the same bank group.</description></item><item><title>DDR4 Overview</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/ddr4-overview/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/ee/mem/ddr4-overview/</guid><description>DDR4 chips comes in x4/8/16/32 configuration, indicating the width of DQ bus being 4/8/16/32 lines.
For pin named XX_n, LOW voltage (referred to as 0) means active/enable, and HIGH (referred as 1) means inactive/disabled.
The operation of a DDR SDRAM chip requires a LOW CS_n signal, otherwise all input will be ignored. This allows multiple chips to use the same command / address bus (as in a memory module), while only the selected one is active.</description></item></channel></rss>