<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Electronic Engineering on Infinity Architect</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/</link><description>Recent content in Electronic Engineering on Infinity Architect</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cesun.info/ee/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Memory Chip MISC</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/misc/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/ee/misc/</guid><description>Data Strobe Encoding To transmit binary bit sequence in a synchronous circuit, one can use a single serial line data, e.g. sampled at the up edge of clock. Data strobe encoding does the same with an extra line strobe, and provide jitter tolerance and clock recovery.
data as before is trasmitted as-is. Level of strobe is flipped only if 2 consecutive data bits are the same. consequence:
data can be verified by looking at strobe data XOR strobe recovers the clock square wave Surface-mount technology (SMT) The technique to install chips on the surface of a PCB, instead of the old way (known as through-hole technology) of penetrating the PCB for holes with metal contacts.</description></item><item><title>Memorandum: Transistors</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/transistors/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/ee/transistors/</guid><description>A transistor is just a variable resistor whose resistance is adjustable not by hand but by electricity.
A transistor is any device with 3 (or more - see below) terminals where the voltage (thus current) between one pair of terminals controls the current (thus effective resistance) flowing through another pair of terminals. This nice controllability allows a transistor to be used as a switch of current, turned on and off also by electricity.</description></item><item><title>A Simple Electric Physics Primer</title><link>https://cesun.info/ee/physics-primer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cesun.info/ee/physics-primer/</guid><description>resistor / resistance &amp;amp; conductance resistance measures an object&amp;rsquo;s opposition to the flow of current through it. conductance is the reciprocal of resistance. (unit: mho ℧) The electrical component that provides resistance is called a resistor.
inductor / inductance When the current (strength) through an object changes (e.g. in an AC circuit), inductance measures the object&amp;rsquo;s ability to oppose such change. Unit of inductance is henry (H). Customary symbol for inductance is L.</description></item></channel></rss>